{
  "reference_number": "9790",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "I strongly support the immediate creation of a Zero Carbon Act.The 2050 target must be set in legislation as soon as possible, as\n time is very short. It is urgent that a strong Climate Commission is set up to reduce NZ’s emissions to meet targets set by the Paris\n Accord. Business as Usual will mean the 1.5C target will be exceeded in 2 to 3 years and the 2C target in 16 to 17 years."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "The options set out in the discussion document are inadequate as they do not address the risk posed by increasing levels of\n methane identified by recent scientific research. It is essential that NZ’s relatively high methane emissions are reduced as well as\n\n CO2 emissions. The gases are very different and will require different approaches that should be developed by a scientifically literate\n Climate Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "The NZ ETS system has been woefully inadequate in producing emissions reductions. In fact it appears to have led to emissions\n increasing. Replacement by a \"feebate\" scheme is required - high emitters should pay heavy fees to be passed on to zero or low\n\n emitters. New forest planting can be a temporary measure only. Ideally there should be a gross emissions target including\n decarbonization of electricity, energy and transport systems (closure of Tiwai Point smelter would achieve this instantly). Methane\n\n emissions should be reduced to much lower levels than at present, though not necessarily to zero."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Revision should be in the direction of stricter controls rather than relaxing goals, unless the circumstances are in some way\n disastrous - the certain worsening of climate change will be the real disaster."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Will the Climate Change Commission determine budgets and strongly recommend them to the Government?"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Changes in budgets should always be in the direction of stronger emission controls."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Again there should be extreme caution about whether emission reduction targets are being weakened."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "However, again there should be extreme caution about whether \"economic and fiscal\" factors are being used as an excuse to carry\non with something close to \"Business as Usual\"."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Plans should be developed with strong input from the independent Climate Change Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "It is critical that the government follows the best science advice available and keeps reviewing policies as the science develops.\nSeparate methodologies must be used for each of the greenhouse gases, CO2, CH4 and N2O. It is very important to follow progress\n\nin other countries. The current Paris Accord pledges do not meet the RCP 2.6 target and will need to be increased. Current research\nshows that increases in methane concentration have not been taken into account in the data used for the Paris Accord and that RCP\n2.6 will have to be urgently revised. This has huge implications for NZ with its Greenhouse Gas emissions profile heavily weighted by\n\nmethane."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Extremely important that the Climate Change Commission is effective in advising on and monitoring NZ's progress towards its goals,\nusing the best available data from a scientifically established and trustworthy monitoring programme."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "As discussed in section 3, the current ETS has been totally ineffective in reducing Greenhouse Gas emissions, particularly through\n\npurchase of \"junk\" overseas units. A \"feebate\" scheme would recover credibility so far totally lost by the current ETS. If this scheme is\nnot used, a completely transparent ETS would have to be established covering all aspects of NZ industry and agriculture. The Climate\n\nChange Commission could investigate whether the ETS should exist at all."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I give qualified agreement here. There should be more emphasis on scientific and engineering expertise from those who understand\ntechnical aspects of Climate Change issues."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The Zero Carbon Act when passed into law must be about following the extremely urgent pathways required to meet and most likely\nexceed pledges made for the Paris Accord, using best practice science strictly monitored by the Climate Change Commission.\n\nAdapting to climate change is an important topic, but should be handled by other advisory groups set up for this specific purpose.\nCentral government should be responsible for setting up these groups to provide a nationwide set of plans, but this should not be a\n\nresponsibility of the Climate Change Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "As discussed in section 14, these functions should not be a responsibility of the Climate Change Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Again, this is required, but should not be a responsibility of the Climate Change Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Productivity Commission's report (April 2018) on \"A Low Emissions Economy\" is a very important, detailed and comprehensive\n\ndocument that should be consulted for many aspects of the Zero Carbon Bill."
    }
  ]
}
